hi my name is Joe brewer and I'd like to
talk with you for a moment about the
power of design for solving the world's
most difficult problems now it's
commonly thought that design is
something that applies to making cute
trinkets or too pretty making pretty
pictures or to making dessert products
that work in a certain way what I want
to do is suggest that design is
something much deeper than that see
design is a process through which one
establishes the criteria for a certain
system to work in a particular way so
for example we have a global financial
system designed specifically to work a
certain way principally to take the
abrogation of capital or money and use
it to leverage that capital to generate
more capital or more money and that is
something that is a set by design to
make the priority that money generation
from money is the primary outcome for
that whole system now there's been a
fair amount of recognition that perhaps
this isn't the best way to design an
economy and that there might be a better
ways to think of what a financial system
should do and our financial system
should be designed and so in this sense
the discussion of design isn't simply
about aesthetics it isn't simply about
selling products it's about identifying
the deep underlying motivations for
creating a set of human activities and
for considering how the institutional
structures the procedures the rules for
that system should be set up to operate
to achieve some goals or some outcomes
that are deemed preferable over others
so when we're talking about designing a
financial system this is exactly what
we're talking about in a more general
sense when we consider that the most
pressing challenges in the world whether
it's from climate change having
potentially catastrophic effects for
human civilization or it's the depletion
of vital resources that our entire
economy depends upon such as oil or the
increasing scarcity of water
or rare earth metals that are used for
making electronics it just does a couple
of examples that in considering these
really challenging problems the only way
that we could envision a solution is to
bring the methods of design to both
critique what the nature the problems
are and where they come from and also to
inspire the kinds of solutions that are
desirable and we're already starting to
see this for example to go back to the
financial sector there's been a growing
recognition that finance is set up in a
way that is oftentimes antithetical to
democratic process by which I mean that
those who have money have undue or
unfair influence over public systems
over government and so those who don't
have money you don't have the ability to
leverage aggregated capital for
influencing political outcomes they are
at a distinct disadvantage and so the
creation of a financial system that's
working quote-unquote properly by the
design criteria I mentioned earlier will
lead to outcomes that are antithetical
to democracy so there's this discussion
going on now about how a financial
system can be designed to become more
democratic and one of the areas that's
particularly interesting to look at is
at the intersection between small-scale
financing what's often called micro
financing and what might also be called
participatory finance the most common
version of that being crowdfunding where
a large number of people each contribute
small amounts of money but interact in a
in a direct and active way with the way
that the money is spent and what the
activities that come out of the money
that's aggregated by that process so
there's a kind of collaboration that
happens so in this sense there are
design criteria being explored to
discover what they are and how they work
that would promote a more interactive
democratic and empowering approach to
pooling in spin
money often times with specific social
goods such as reducing poverty
increasing human well-being or
addressing environmental concerns become
the measures of success so in situations
like these it becomes increasingly clear
that considerations of design are at the
center of the discussion so anyone who
wants to engage in solving the big
problems is going to need to learn more
about design and is going to act as a
designer in considering what those webs
of human activities and the systems that
kind of architecting of those systems
are where they're deficient and what the
motivations are to solve them this is
something that I'm of course quite
interested in seeing more of and as a
designer myself seek to bring insights
from cognitive science and Earth System
science and from organizational strategy
and social change to bear on global
problems but I'm by no means the only
one doing this there's an increasing
number of people who recognize that many
of the problems in that we have in the
world whether ecological or social or
political economic or what have you or
what might be considered to be symptoms
of bad design and that good design can
help to solve them so that's just a bit
of thinking about how design can help
solve global problems and I hope that it
encourages you to put on your design hat
roll up your sleeves and get involved
thank you